# Sooyong Lee

PHD

Educational Psychology, The University of Texas at Austin

□ +1 737 865 0618 | Sooyongl09@gmail.com | 00000-0002-7964-4508 | Sooyongl/

# Professional Summary \_\_\_\_\_

As a psychometrician, I specialize in applying contemporary statistical theories and techniques to my work. My research interests center around developing and utilizing statistical models, including structural equation modeling (SEM), multilevel modeling (MLM), item response theory (IRT), and mixture modeling. In my recent work, I have placed particular emphasis on Bayesian estimation as a means of modeling the relationships between variables.

## Education

#### The University of Texas at Austin

Austin, Texas

Ph.D., Major in Quantitative Methods in Educational Psychology

2017-2023

• Dissertation: Development of a Method for Addressing Various Censoring Effects in a Latent Growth Curve Modeling Framework. Advisor: Tiffany Whittaker

Korea University Seoul, Republic of Korea

M.A., MAJOR IN EDUCATIONAL STATISTICS AND MEASUREMENT

2014-2017

• Thesis: Exploration of LCA conditions in Latent Class with Low Proportion. Advisore: Sehee Hong

## **Publications**

#### 2023

- Jonghwan Lee, Christina Schneider, Garron Gianopulos, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, Sangdon Lim, & Seung W Choi (2023). The Impact of Item Bank Transition Rules on Student Ability Estimates and Achievement Level Classifications. *Journal of Computerized Adaptive Testing*. In print.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2023). Bayesian Moderated Non-linear Factor Analysis for DIF Detection under Violation of Equal Variance Assumption. *Educational and Psychological Measurement*. Under review.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Fully Latent Principal Stratification With Measurement Models. *Journal of Educational and Behavioral Statistics*. Under review.
- Rene M. Dailey, ..., & **Sooyong Lee** (2023). Testing A Comprehensive Model of Post-Dissolution Distress: Predicting Initial and Over Time Changes in Distress Following Romantic Dissolution among U.S. Adults. *Journal of Personality and Social Psychology*. Under review.
- Kahyun Lee, **Sooyong Lee**, & Allison Master (2023). From Fixed to Growth: An Intensive Longitudinal Study of the Interplay Between Growth Mindset, Emotions, Sense of Belonging, and Experiences in Daily Life Among College Students. In preparation.
- Kahyun Lee, **Sooyong Lee**, & Allison Master (2023). Exploring the Dynamics of Daily Experiences, Emotions, and Depression among Asian American Students: The Moderating Role of Growth Mindsets. In preparation.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Bayesian and Maximum Likelihood Estimation in Fully Latent Principal Stratification. In preparation.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Multidimensional Fully-latent Principal Stratification. In preparation.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Suyoung Kim, & Jiwon Kim (2023). Investigating Latent Interaction Effects in Multiple-Group Analysis in the Structural Equation Modeling Framework. In preparation.

- Tiffany A. Whittaker, Laura Stapleton & **Sooyong Lee** (2023). A Tutorial for Obtaining Item Response Theory Results from Structural Equation Modeling in Mplus Software with Rating Scales. In preparation.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Parallel Process Latent Growth Modeling with Multivariate Confounders/Suppresson Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal. 30(2), 284-295.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Kahyun Lee, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Application of Associative Discrete-Time Survival Analysis Using Latent Transition Specification. *Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary Journal*. 1-12.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2023). Fully Latent Principal Stratification: Combining PS with Model-Based Measurement Models.. *The Annual Meeting of the Psychometric Society*. pp. 287-298.

#### 2022

- Seung Choi, Sangdon Lim, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, Christina M. Schneider, Jay Lee, & Garron J. (2022). maat: An R Package for Multiple Administrations Adaptive Testing. *Applied Psychological Measurement*. 46-1, 73-74. DOI:10.1177/01466216211049212.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2022). DIF Detection With Zero-Inflation Under the Factor Mixture Modeling Framework. *Educational and Psychological Measurement*. 82-4, 678-704. DOI: 10.1177/00131644211028995.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2022). Comparison of Three Approaches to Class Enumeration in Growth Mixture Modeling when Time Structures are Variant Across Latent Classes. *Structural Equation Modeling: A Multi-disciplinary Journal*. 29, 23-35. DOI:10.1080/10705511.2021.1956320.

#### 2021

Cory L. Cobb, Charles R. Martínez, Jr., **Sooyong Lee**, Tae Kyoung Lee, & Elma I. Lorenzo-Blanco (2021). Acculturation trajectories differ by youth age at arrival and time in residency among Latino immigrant families in a US emerging immigrant context. *International Journal of Intercultural Relations*. 81, 79-93. DOI:10.1016/j.ijintrel. 2021.01.005.

#### 2016

- **Sooyong Lee**, Eun Soo Lee, & Sehee Hong (2016). Effects of adolescent's career development on labor market outcoms: Applying the two0part growth mixture model. *Journal of Vocational Education & Training*. 19(3), 137-162.
- Eun Soo Lee, **Sooyong Lee**, & Sehee Hong (2016). The Effects of Community Child-Center Service on School Adjustment Change Trajectory. *Korean Journal of Social Wellfare Research*. 50, 59-85.

#### Presentation \_

#### **Presentation**

- Tiffany Whittaker, Hyeon-Ah Kang, **Sooyong Lee**, Adam Sales (2023-04). *Bayesian and Maximum Likelihood Estimation in Fully Latent Principal Stratification*. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), Chicago, USA.
- **Sooyong Lee**, Adam Sales, Hyeon-Ah Kang, & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2022-07). *Fully-Latent Principal Stratilication*. International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), Bologna, Italy.
- Garron Gianopulos, Jay Lee, Sangdon Lim, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, & Seung W. Choi (2022-04). *The Impact of Item Pool Size and Item Pool Distribution on Student Ability Estimates for a Hybrid Interim-Summative CAT*. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), San Diego, USA.
- Jay Lee, M. Christina Schneider, Garron Gia, Luping Niu, **Sooyong Lee**, Sangdon Lim, & Seung W. Choi (2022-04). *The Impact of item bank transition rules on student ability estimates and achievement level classifications*. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), San Diego, USA.

Daniel Lewis & **Sooyong Lee** (2021-04). *A Comparison of Two ESS Cut Score Estimation Algorithms*. National Council on Measurement in Education (NCME), Baltimore, MD, USA.

#### **Poster**

- **Sooyong Lee**, Suhwa Han, & Seung W. Choi (2021-04). *DIF Detection with Zero-Inflation under the Mixture Modeling Framework*. American Educational Research Association (AERA), Virtual.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Suhwa Han (2020-07). *Item selection and trait estimation methods in CAT with item leakage*. International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), Maryland, USA.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Tiffany A. Whittaker (2020-04). *Comparison of Three Approaches to Class Enumeration in Growth Mixture Modeling when Time Structures are Variant Across Latent Classes*. American Educational Research Association (AERA), Virtual.
- **Sooyong Lee** & Sehee Hong (2018-07). *Exploration of LCA conditions in Latent Class with Low Proportion*. International Meeting of the Psychometric Society (IMPS), New York, USA.
- Kejin Lee, **Sooyong Lee**, & Youngri Lee (2018-05). *An Alternative Approach to Discrete-Time Survival Analysis for Meaningful Interpretation*. Modern Modeling Methods conference (MMM), Connecticut, USA.

# Research experience \_\_\_\_\_

FLPS project
Post-doc fellow
IES GRANT
2023/9-present

• Development of FLPS package for Fully-latent Principal Stratification

FLPS project

IES GRANT

Graduate Research Assistant
2021/9-2023/8

• Development of FLPS package for Fully-latent Principal Stratification

#### **Embedded Standard Setting (ESS)**

Intern

CREATIVE MEASUREMENT SOLUTIONS LLC

2021/6-2021/8

Internship for developing ESS package for Embeded Standard Setting

#### **Embedded Standard Setting (ESS)**

Intern

CREATIVE MEASUREMENT SOLUTIONS LLC

2020/6-2020/8

Internship for developing Shiny app for Embedded Standard Setting

#### maat package development project

Graduate Research Assistant

NORTHWEST EVALUATION ASSOCIATION (NWEA)

2019/9-2020/5

Development of MAAT package for Computerized Adaptive Testing for Northwest Evaluation Association (NWEA)

#### **COE Full-Time Tenured and Tenure-Track Faculty**

Graduate Research Assistant

2019/9-2019/12

• Data analysis for surveys of graduate programs of education at the University of Texas at Austin

### President's Award for Global Learning (PAGL)

Graduate Research Assistant

PRESIDENT'S AWARD FOR GLOBAL LEARNING (PAGL)

2019/1-2019/8

• Designing a culturally appropriate mobile application to increase mental health literacy and self-care habits among South Korean young adults

#### **CGS PhD Career Pathways project**

Graduate Research Assistant

2018/9-2019/5

• Data analysis for surveys to collect data on the career pathways of past and present STEM and humanities PhD students.

Teaching experience	
EDP 380C: Structural Equation Modeling Professor Tiffany Whittaker	Teaching Assistant 2021/1-2021/5
EDP 380C: Structural Equation Modeling Professor Tiffany Whittaker	Teaching Assistant 2020/1-2020/5
Program	
<pre>GRshiny package • https://sooyongl.github.io/GRShiny/</pre>	R package 2023
<pre>clavaan package • https://github.com/sooyongl/clavaan</pre>	R package 2023
<pre>GRshiny: Graded response model • https://sooyonglee.shinyapps.io/GRShiny/</pre>	Shiny application 2022
<pre>Embeded Standard Setting • https://sooyongl.github.io/EmStanS/</pre>	R package 2022
<pre>maat package • https://choi-phd.github.io/maat/</pre>	R package 2022
<pre>flps package • https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/flps/index.html</pre>	R package 2022
<pre>Embeded Standard Setting • https://sooyonglee.shinyapps.io/ESS_shiny/</pre>	Shiny application 2021
Service	
International Journal of Intercultural Relations	Reviewer 2023/7 - present
Fellowship & Awards	
2021-22 Benjamin & Dorothy Fruchter Excellence Award 2020-21 William Hays Endowed Fellowship	Award Fellowship